Omaha Indian interviews collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Omaha Indian interviews collection, 1999 1999
AFC 1999/014
Jabbour, Alan; McIntyre, Laurel
approximately 454 items
3 containers
17 folders.
1 computer disk.
26 sound tape reels: analog, 7 1/2 and 3 3/4 ips; 7 in.
1 sound cassette (60 min.): analog.
184 photographs: negatives, photographic prints, black and white.
22 photographs: prints, black and white; 8 x 10 in.
5 photographs: contact sheets, black and white; 8 x 10 in.
2 posters; various sizes
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Manuscript, sound recordings, and graphic materials collected by Alan Jabbour and Laurel McIntyre during four visits in 1999 to Macy, Nebraska, in an effort to identify sound recordings and photographic images from the American Folklife Center's Omaha Indian collections. Hethu’shka song translations and contextual information were gathered in recorded interviews with Omaha tribe members Rufus White, Elmer Blackbird, and Morgan Lovejoy.
Provenance
Alan Jabbour and Laurel McIntyre conducted and recorded the interviews and took the photographs in this collection for the American Folklife Center.
Related Material
The present collection was a result of preparatory work on the Omaha Indian Music presentation, which is available at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000007. This online presentation contains photographs and sound recordings featuring the traditional Omaha music from the 1983 Omaha harvest celebration pow-wow, the 1985 Hethu'shka Society concert at the Library of Congress, and the wax cylinder recordings of Francis La Flesche and Alice Cunningham Fletcher made from 1895 to 1897.
The present collection contains context, commentary and identifications related to the following collections which are also included in the online presentation:
1985 Neptune Plaza Concert Series collection (AFC 1985/015)
Alice C. Fletcher and Francis La Flesche collection of Omaha cylinder recordings (AFC 1948/123)
Alan Jabbour/Omaha Indian interviews collection (AFC 1983/026: AFS 22620-22625)
Omaha Indian Pow-Wow collection (AFC 1986/038)
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact.
Listening copies of the recordings are available at the Folklife Reading Room and excerpts are available online at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000007.
Reference copies of materials from this collection were given to the Omaha Branch of the Nebraska Indian Community College (NICC).
Online Content
Portions of this collection are available on the Library of Congress Web site in the online collection Omaha Indian Music at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000007. Where available, links to specific online content are available in the contents list of this finding aid.
Scope and Content
Manuscript, sound recordings, and graphic materials collected by Alan Jabbour and Laurel McIntyre during four visits in 1999 to Macy, Nebraska, in an effort to identify sound recordings and photographic images from the American Folklife Center's Omaha Indian collections. This project was undertaken as part of the National Digital Library Program's effort to obtain information on materials to be used in the Omaha Indian Music online presentation.
Hethu’shka song translations and contextual information were gathered in recorded interviews with Omaha tribe members Rufus White, Elmer Blackbird, and Morgan Lovejoy. The interviewees listened to and commented on sound recordings from the collections of the American Folklife Center. These included Hethu’shka songs from the 1890s, the 1983 Omaha harvest celebration pow-wow, Alan Jabbour’s 1983 interview with John Turner, and the Hethu’shka Society performance in the 1985 Neptune Plaza Concert Series at the Library of Congress. The interviews are conducted by Alan Jabbour and Laurel McIntyre. Dennis Hastings, director of the Omaha Tribal Historical Research Project, was consulted throughout this project for help identifying subjects in photographs.
Arrangement
The manuscripts and graphic materials are arranged chronologically. Each roll of film has been housed in an individual negative sleeve and prints from each roll of film are housed and grouped together in individual folders. Original oversized posters are housed in Box 2.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Blackbird, Elmer; Hastings, Dennis.; Jabbour, Alan; Lovejoy, Morgan; McIntyre, Laurel; White, Rufus
Organizations
American Folklife Center; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); Hethu'shka Society.
Subjects
Dance music--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.; Indian veterans--Omaha Indian Reservation--Songs and music.; Omaha dance.; Omaha dialect.; Omaha Indians--Music.; Omaha Indians--Nebraska--Social life and customs.; Omaha Indians--Religion.; Omaha Indians--Rites and ceremonies.; Omaha Indians--Songs and music.; Powwow songs--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.; Powwows--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.
Places
Macy (Neb.) event place.; Omaha Indian Reservation (Neb.)--Social life and customs--20th century.
Form/Genre
Dance music.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Photographs.; Posters.; Powwow songs.; Songs.
Contents List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Finding aids., 34 pages. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Administrative—Donation to Nebraska Indian Community College, Summer 1999., 5 pages. (Box-folder 1/2)
    Gift documentation.
  - Administrative—General Correspondence, October 2, 1998-October 2, 1999., 64 pages. (Box-folder 1/3)
    Administrative correspondence regarding planning and follow-up of interviews.
  - Administrative—Contracts, June 21, 1999-October 16, 1999., 38 pages. (Box-folder 1/4)
    Administrative correspondence, invoices, and contracts regarding hiring and payment for consultants.
  - Administrative—Trip Reports–Jabbour, Alan, April 1, 1999-October 1, 1999., 12 pages. (Box-folder 1/5)
    Short and final reports for each trip to Macy, Nebraska.
  - Administrative—Trip Reports–McIntyre, Laurel, April 1, 1999-August 1, 1999., 31 pages. (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Photograph Identification by Dennis Hastings., 10 pages. (Box-folder 1/7)
    Dennis Hastings notes and identifications of photographs from the 1983 Omaha Pow-Wow.
  - Poster copies., 2 items. (Box-folder 1/8)
    Preservation photocopies of original posters.
    Related material: Original Posters
  - Sound Recordings—Logs. SR001-SR027, July 2, 1999-October 1, 1999., 45 pages. (Box-folder 1/9)
    Final and draft copies of sound recording logs.
  - Sound Recordings—Tape box photocopies. SR001-SR026., 7 pages. (Box-folder 1/10)
    Photocopies of notes on the backs of sound recording containers.
- Series 2: Sound Recordings, 26 7-inch reels, 1 60-minute audiocassette.
  - Interview of Rufus White conducted by Alan Jabbour and Laurel McIntyre regarding recordings from AFC 1986/038, AFC 1948/123, and AFC 1985/015, July 20-23, 1999, 25 sound tape reels
    Includes: Rufus White’s translations of Omaha and commentary on songs sung by the Host Drum and the Tai Piah Singers during the 1983 Omaha pow-wow (AFC 1986/038); White’s commentary on ten Hethu’shka songs that are included on Omaha Indian Music (originally from AFC 1948/123); White’s commentary on the performance by members of the Hethu'shka Society at a 1985 Library of Congress concert (AFC 1985/015); Information about Rufus’s family and John Turner; Tribal Council Chairman Elmer Blackbird comments about the Omaha language and biographical information.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 20, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR001)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Gourd Dance Song, Grand Entry Song (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0376-0388).
      - Commentary on Gourd Dance Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0376), AFC 1999/014: 0748
        Notes from interview: The Gourd Dance Society was performing at the pow-wow. In the Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma, gourd dance songs have been used for social gatherings. The Omaha have used them for birthday celebrations or as veterans' songs. Some gourd dance songs have words, and others do not. Three Gourd Dances, which were not recorded, preceded this song.
      - Commentary on Gourd Dance Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0377), AFC 1999/014: 0749
        Notes from interview: The Gourd Dance Society was performing at the pow-wow. In the Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma, gourd dance songs have been used for social gatherings. The Omaha have used them for birthday celebrations or as veterans' songs. Some gourd dance songs have words, and others do not. This song does not have words.
      - Commentary on Gourd Dance Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0378), AFC 1999/014: 0750
        Notes from interview: The Gourd Dance Society was performing at the pow-wow. In the Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma, gourd dance songs have been used for social gatherings. The Omaha have used them for birthday celebrations or as veterans' songs. Some gourd dance songs have words, and others do not.
      - Commentary on Gourd Dance Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0379), AFC 1999/014: 0751
      - Commentary on Grand Entry Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0388), AFC 1999/014: 0752
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 20, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR002)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Flag Song, Hethu’shka songs (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0389-0391).
      - Commentary on Flag Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0389), AFC 1999/014: 0753
        Notes from interview: This is one of two National Anthem songs that the Omaha sing. It welcomes veterans. A drum is used with this Flag Song. For another Flag Song that is used, there is not a drum. The Flag Song is, in general, only used during the annual pow-wow.
      - Commentary on Flag Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0389), AFC 1999/014: 0754
        Rufus White translates the song: "When he went over there, he put up an American flag."
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0390), AFC 1999/014: 0755
        Rufus White translates the song: "Get up and dance and enjoy yourself. Hurry up and get up." White compares the beat of the drum with the sound of buffalo. He refers to Charlie Edwards.
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0390), AFC 1999/014: 0756
        Rufus White translates the song: "Get up and dance." Notes from interview: This is a traditional song. White has heard this song sung during the Oklahoma pow-wow and tells of the connections that songs can bring about. Hearing the song made him feel like dancing.
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0391), AFC 1999/014: 0757
        Rufus White translates the song: "When I came to your village, I saw your spirit and was thinking of you. My spirit is still here." Notes from interview: The person who made the song cried as he sang it. He saw the spirit as he was singing.
      - Commentary on the Grand Entry, AFC 1999/014: 0758
        Notes from interview: Arena directors used to usher in dancers. There didn't used to be a Grand Entry. The Omaha started using a Grand Entry during the annual pow-wow around the early 1970s.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 20, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR003)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Hethu’shka songs (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0392-0393).
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0392), AFC 1999/014: 0759
        Rufus White translates the song: "The young man is coming home. Get something ready for him." Words include "God help us. Pity us. Thank you for the beautiful things that we can share with one another." Notes from interview: This song has a lot of meaning. The man made four stops before he returned to his people because he was proud that he could bring them food. He saved people's lives. He gave sick elderly people four spoonfulls of everything for four days. Today, things continue to be done four times. For example, four Hethu'shka (Warrior) Songs are sung at the beginning of each pow-wow program and the pow-wow lasts for four days. Emcee Clifford Wolfe, Sr., who was speaking during the song, was saying that it was really good to hear the old songs.
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0393), AFC 1999/014: 0760
        Rufus White translates the song: "When I got up, something was tapping my shoulder." Notes from interview: The wolves were hollering and woke the person up. The person was fasting, but he fell asleep during the last morning of the four days.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR004)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Whipman’s Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0397), and information about his family and John Turner.
      - Commentary on Whipman's Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0397), AFC 1999/014: 0761
        Rufus White translates the song: "Get up. Stand up." Notes from interview: This song is for the whipman, or the head man dancer. A long time ago, whipmen were called Omaha scouts. Three or four men used to encourage people to get up.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR005)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Tail Dancer’s Song, Pow-wow Princess, General Dancing, Hethu’shka songs (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0398-0402).
      - Commentary on Tail Dancers' Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0398), AFC 1999/014: 0762
        Notes from interview: This is an honoring song without words.
      - Commentary on Pow-Wow Princess Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0399), AFC 1999/014: 0763
        Rufus White translates the song: "I'm coming. I'm coming to you." Notes from interview: This song was for Melanie Parker, the pow-wow princess.
      - Commentary on General Dancing Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0400), AFC 1999/014: 0764
        Rufus White translates the song: "The warriors are being honored." Notes from interview: This song has two words.
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0401), AFC 1999/014: 0765
        Notes from interview: This is a song without words.
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0402), AFC 1999/014: 0766
        Rufus White translates the song: "God, look at me. It was hard for me to be a warrior." Notes from interview: One must be honored in order to be a warrior. This song has a lot of meaning for the Omahas.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR006)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Horses Are Afraid of the Enemy Song, General Dancing Song, Hethu’shka songs (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0403-0405, 0413).
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0403), AFC 1999/014: 0767
        Notes from interview: This is a song without words. It is used to encourage people to dance.
      - Commentary on The Horses Are Afraid of the Enemy (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0404), AFC 1999/014: 0768
        Rufus White translates the song: "The enemies are coming. The horses are holding back. They don't want to go to fight the enemy."
      - Commentary on General Dancing Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0413), AFC 1999/014: 0769
        Notes from interview: This is one of numerous "Sioux" songs.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR007)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Hethu’shka songs, Honoring Song, Horse Song, Contest Song Warm-Up (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0414-0415, 0418-0420, 0438).
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0414), AFC 1999/014: 0770
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0415), AFC 1999/014: 0771
      - Commentary on Honoring Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0418), AFC 1999/014: 0772
        Notes from interview: This song was intended to welcome other tribes.
      - Commentary on Honoring Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0419), AFC 1999/014: 0773
      - Commentary on Horse Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0420), AFC 1999/014: 0774
        Notes from interview: This is an older traditional war dance song. It does not have any words.
      - Commentary on Contest Song (Warm-Up) (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0438), AFC 1999/014: 0775
        Notes from interview: This is a fast song!
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR008)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Contest Song, Hethu’shka songs, Half-Breed Song, Grand Finale, Grand Entry, Flag Song (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0439-0440, 0446, 0451-0452, 0454-0458).
      - Commentary on Hethu'shka Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0440), AFC 1999/014: 0776
        Rufus White translates the song: "Pity him. They (the Omahas) wounded him." Notes from interview: There are two ways that this song could be sung. This is one of the four traditional songs sung at the beginning of the pow-wow, but its wording is a little different. This is sung from the point of view of the enemy.
      - Commentary on Half-Breed Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0446), AFC 1999/014: 0777
        Notes from interview: Louie Saunsoci made this song for half-breeds. It was sung for Louie Dick.
      - Commentary on Flag Song, AFC 1999/014: 0778
        Rufus White translates the song: "When you went overseas, you made a stand so that the flag could be raised. When you returned, you brought the flag back. You saved our lives." Notes from interview: This song is usually sung at the end of a program; it is a quitting song.
      - Commentary on Flag Song, AFC 1999/014: 0779
      - Commentary on Grand Finale Song, AFC 1999/014: 0780
        Rufus White translates the song: "Stand up. We are going out."
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR009)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Hethu’shka Song, Tail Dancer’s Song (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0459-0460, 0462).
      - Commentary on Song Sung in Place of the Whipman's Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0460), AFC 1999/014: 0781
        Notes from interview: This is a song without words. The other drum was helping the Host Drum, and the Whipman's Song was not actually sung.
      - Commentary on Tail Dancers' Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0462), AFC 1999/014: 0782
        Rufus White translates the song: "Get up and dance. Get up! Get up and dance!" Notes from interview: This is another song that was used for the tail dancers.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR010)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Tiny Tots’ Shawl Dance Contest Song, Junior Girls’ Shawl Dance, Tiny Tots’ Fancy Dance, Little Boys’ Fancy Dance, Junior Boys’ Fancy Dance (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0472, 0474-0475, 0477, 0480-0481, 0483, 0485).
      - Commentary on Tiny Tots' Shawl Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0472), AFC 1999/014: 0783
        Rufus White translates the song: "Hurry up. Get up." Notes from interview: This song has two words.
      - Commentary on Junior Girls' Shawl Dance Contest Song (Warm-Up) (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0474), AFC 1999/014: 0784
        Rufus White translates the song: "Stand up. Get up." Notes from interview: This is a "straight traditional song" without words.
      - Commentary on Junior Girls' Shawl Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0475), AFC 1999/014: 0785
        Notes from interview: This is a really old song. The song was made for a medicine man who brought his wagon into the arena. He was grateful for the song and hollered around the drum four times. He gave gifts to everyone. John Turner sang a similar song.
      - Commentary on Tiny Tots' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0477), AFC 1999/014: 0786
        Rufus White translates the song: "Run fast. Run as fast as you can. The people are whistling by." Notes from interview: This is a contest song that was made for fancy dancers. The horse was running and came to a complete stop, just as the fancy dancers do.
      - Commentary on Tiny Tots' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0480), AFC 1999/014: 0787
        Rufus White translates the song: "Hurry up. Go as fast as you can. Get away from the one who is chasing." Notes from interview: Anyone, including non-Omahas, could request that this song be sung. It belongs to everybody.
      - Commentary on Tiny Tots' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0481), AFC 1999/014: 0788
        Notes from interview: This is a Kiowa song. The man who made the song requested that the Host Drum sing it. He paid the singers, as is customary when a request is made.
      - Commentary on Little Boys' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0483), AFC 1999/014: 0789
        Rufus White translates the song: "When you're getting out there, holler. When you're enjoying yourself, holler." Notes from interview: The song from which this contest song was made has two words.
      - Commentary on Junior Boys' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Warm-Up) (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0485), AFC 1999/014: 0790
        Notes from interview: This is a song without words. It can be sung for anyone.
    - Rufus White’s commentary on 1983 Omaha pow-wow songs, July 21, 1999, sound tape reel, analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Tape AFC 1999/014: SR011)
      Includes playback of and commmentary on Junior Boys’ Fancy Dance, Song for All Dancers, Song for Paul Brill Special, Regular Pow-wow Song, Junior Girls’ Shawl Dance (Call Numbers: AFC 1986/038: 0486-0487, 0489, 0493-0494, 0496).
      - Commentary on Junior Boys' Fancy Dance Contest Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0486), AFC 1999/014: 0791
        Rufus White translates the song: "Duck and run. The enemy is throwing something at you. Run away as fast as you can." Notes from interview: This song has a lot of meaning to the Omahas.
      - Commentary on Song for All of the Dancers (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0487), AFC 1999/014: 0792
        Rufus White translates the song: "I don't have any friends." Notes from interview: This song was made by an old man while he was fasting. He made the song for his grandson who now lives in Germany. It conveys that a person may not have friends when he or she is in a new place. It is a song that can be used for all dancers.
      - Commentary on Song During Paul Brill Special (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0489), AFC 1999/014: 0793
        Rufus White translates the song: "God, watch over us. I am the warrior, but it is hard for me to take this position." Notes from interview: Paul Brill, who used to work on the Omaha reservation, requested this song.
      - Commentary on Regular Pow-Wow Song (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0493), AFC 1999/014: 0794
        Rufus White translates the song: "You made the other tribes cry."
      - Commentary on One More Song Before Dancers Clear the Arena (Call Number: AFC 1986/038: 0494), AFC 1999/014: 0795